Guide to the Papers of Lawrence Winston 1938-1945 MS 2
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Lawrence Winston Papers
1938-1945
MS 2
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.08 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Lawrence Winston was an African American United States Navy sailor who served aboard the USS Mugford and the USS General M.M. Patrick during World War II. The USS Mugford, a destroyer, was stationed at Pearl Harbor during the attack on December 7, 1941. This collection contains approximately three hundred and fifty letters written by Lawrence Winston to his wife Cecelia Winston, including forty V-mails.
Provenance
Purchase, 2006
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Lawrence Winston, an African American United States Navy sailor, served aboard the USS Mugford, 1938-1944 and the USS General M.M. Patrick, 1944-[]. The USS Mugford, a destroyer, was stationed at Pearl Harbor, December 7, 1941.
Winston joined the Navy in 1936 and re-enlisted in November, 1941. He started dating Cecelia Little in the fall of 1936 while he was at the Annapolis Naval Academy. He married her in 1938 and she gave birth to their first child, Patricia Anne, later that year. They had another girl in September of 1940, Charlotte.
Winston was transferred to Boston in May of 1938 where he began his service aboard the USS Mugford. This destroyer was stationed at numerous locations prior to the war including: Panama; Guantanamo, Cuba; Gonaives, Haiti; San Juan, Puerto Rico; Port Au Prince; San Diego, CA; Pearl Harbor, HI; and Japan. After the bombing of Pearl Harbor, Winston's ship was involved in campaigns in the South Pacific--including the Guadalcanal landings and operations in New Guinea and the Solomon and Marshall Islands. In February, 1944 the USS Mugford returned to the U.S. for overhaul. Lawrence was transferred to the USS General M.M. Patrick, which launched in June of 1944. This ship transported military personnel and traveled to numerous locations including: Pearl Harbor; Guam; the Philippines; Australia; and Calcutta, India.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains approximately three hundred and fifty letters written from 1938 to 1945, primarily by Lawrence Winston to his wife Cecelia Winston. Additionally, the collection includes several letters written by Lawrence to various relatives (his mother, father, daughter Pat, and father-in-law) and several letters written to Cecelia from her relatives.
The correspondence contains a number of letters written while Lawrence was stationed at Pearl Harbor, from pre-war through early 1942. Although there are no descriptive letters about the attack, the collection contains two items from December of 1941. As all mail was censored for sensitive material during the war, Lawrence Winston does not write about his location or activities. Therefore, much of the content of the letters of this period regards his personal feelings towards his wife and daughters and domestic issues such as finances.
Highlights of the correspondence include: a 1938 letter describing the negro condition in Panama and the nature of Panamanians in general; descriptions of the natives in Port Au Prince and their differing treatment of negroes and whites; a letter dated November, 1941 discussing the delicate war crisis written after Lawrence's return from Japan; descriptions of his physical and mental deterioration due to bombings and the stress of being away from home for nearly four years straight; and some letters revealing the experience of African American sailors in the Navy.
In addition to the typed and hand-written letters the collections contain 40 V-mails, several telegrams and postcards, and a few ephemeral items.
Arrangement
Letters are arranged chronologically.
USS General M.M. Patrick (AP-150); USS Mugford (Destroyer: DD-389); Winston, Cecelia; Winston, Lawrence; Correspondence; Ephemera; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941; Postcards; Telegrams; United States. Navy African Americans; V-mail; World War, 1939-1945 Naval operations
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1938 Apr.- 1938 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1938 Oct.- 1938 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1939 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1939 Feb.- 1939 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1939 May - 1939 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1939 Aug.- 1939 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1940 Mar.- 1940 May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1940 June - 1940 July (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1940 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1940 Sept.- 1940 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1941 Jan.- 1941 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1941 July - 1941 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1942 Jan.- 1942 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1943 Jan.- 1943 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1943 Aug.- 1943 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1943 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1943 Nov.- 1943 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1944 Jan.- 1944 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1944 Apr.- 1944 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1944 Sept.- 1944 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1945 Mar.- 1945 June (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia Winston, 1945 July - 1945 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Incomplete or undated correspondence to Cecelia Winston (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to mother, father, daughter Pat, and father-in-law, 1938-1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Cecelia from her relatives, 1938-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Postcards, telegrams, ephemera, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Empty envelopes from Lawrence to Cecelia, 1938-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Empty envelopes to Cecelia from others, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)